Finding Aid for David V. Tinder Collection of Michigan Photography, County File, Wayne County, 1865-1985
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
David V. Tinder Collection of Michigan Photography, County File, Wayne County1865-1985
Tinder, David V., Collection of Michigan Photography, County File, Wayne County
Tinder, David V.
1,937 photographs, 16 real photo stamps, 6 booklets, 101 pages, clippings and ephemera
wclgrfx000200
The collection contains photographs of Wayne County, Michigan. Included are numerous urban scenes and images of everyday life, primarily in the Metropolitan Detroit area between 1860 and the mid-20th century. The bulk of the photographs were taken between 1890 and 1930. A very wide range of topics is represented, among them commercial and residential architecture, urban infrastructure, public and private spaces, civic and domestic activities, individual and group portraits, and events from across the social spectrum.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
F-832, F-860, F-861, F-891, F-892, F-893, F-898, F-909, F-911, F-914, F-922, F-938, F-940, F-945, F-961, F-980, F-987, F-1004, F-1005, F-1014, F-1017, F-1027, F-1028, F-1033, F-1054, F-1066, F-1067, F-1074, F-1076, F-1077, F-1113, F-1114.
The collection is open to research.
History
The city of Detroit and its vast metropolitan area has dominated the Wayne County area for centuries. Detroit was founded in 1701 as a French settlement with access to the Great Lakes and Canada and quickly became a strategic military post and trade center. It transferred to British control in 1760 during the Seven Years War and to United States governance in 1796. It became a chartered city in 1802, the capitol of the Michigan Territory in 1805, and Michigan’s first State Capital from 1837 to 1847. The city grew with an economy based largely on agriculture and trade in the early 19th century, becoming one of the nation’s prime manufacturing and cultural centers after the Civil War. Large industries based in the region included railroad equipment manufacturing, ship building, iron and steel production, stoves, pharmaceuticals, brewing, wagon making, and many others.
The industrial strength of Detroit created a large middle-class society as well as vast wealth. In turn, this affluence supported cultural advancement, education, and the arts. Commercial photography studios thrived in this environment. Many prize-winning portrait photographers were based in Detroit, as were those specializing in architecture, and the documentation of industry and commerce.
The diversity of industry of late 19th century Detroit gave way to automobile centered growth in the mid-20th century. The boom in wartime production during World War Two attracted workers from around the country and shifted the racial demographics of the city.
The collapse of manufacturing industries, the disappearance of public transportation, and massive population shifts to the suburbs were factors in the decline of Detroit in the mid to late 20th century.
Included in the Wayne County file of the David V. Tinder Collection of Michigan Photography are images of urban Detroit, people in their places of work, at home, at leisure, and participating in social activities and in fraternal and religious organizations. Numerous images show industrial manufacturing, urban transportation, and civic infrastructure. Activities related to entertainment, sports, parades, and the arts are well represented. The many portraits photographs include formal posed images, casual snapshots, workplace groups and fraternal organizations.
A vast majority of the photographs are the work of commercial photographers, with some amateurs. A significant number of photos were taken by Detroit News and Detroit Free Press photographers. Almost all the images present would be considered vernacular photos rather than fine art; however, many are carefully composed with strong aesthetic characteristics.
Although the photos have been largely sorted by subject, related materials may be present outside of the subject categories, i.e., images of transportation can also be found in the categories Architecture, Business and Commerce, Group Portraits, and in other sections outside of Transportation.
The bulk of the photos in this collection were taken in Detroit during the era of rapid population growth and industrial development around the turn of the century. The diversity of industry that appears in the late 19th century images can be seen giving way to automobile centered growth in the mid-20th century. Evidence of the rich residential lifestyles and multi-ethnic cultures of the Detroit area appear in many images.
At the fringe of the collection’s scope are images of the demolition of factories, the disappearance of public transportation, and racial unrest during the decline of Detroit in the mid to late 20th century.
It should be noted that while most of the collection are mounted and unmounted photographic prints, there are a few bound items as well as printed ephemera.
The collection has been organized into various categories by subject. The first group of photos is comprised of those that did not fit neatly under other categories. These include views of military encampments, disasters and firefighting, civic unrest, commercial product promotions, and other miscellaneous topics. Of particular note is a charming outdoor children’s party scene by amateur photographer Robert R. Oesterreich (no. 9); a double portrait montage by Tony Spina of John F. Kennedy and Robert F. Kennedy, both speaking at Campus Martius (no. 14); the high quality photomechanical prints of Detroit scenes and architecture in the Detroit Illustrated. (no. 16); and a collection of 28 miscellaneous nightclub souvenir photographs dating from the 1940s-1980s (no. 20). The rest of the material falls under the following categories:
Transportation:
243 photographs. Material is divided between the following sub-categories: Automobiles and Trucks (56 photographs), Aircraft (18 photographs), Railroads and Trains (58 photographs), Streetcars and Trolleys (20 photographs), Roads and Infrastructure (33 photographs), Wagons (20 photographs), Maritime (38 photographs).
Of note are a photograph of an African American couple posed with a new V-8 Ford (no. 71.3); construction photos of the Detroit River railroad tunnel (no. 95); Goebel’s Brewing Co. delivery wagons (no. 98); and a view of the steamboat Tashmoo at speed on the Detroit River (no. 110).
Performers:
107 photographs, most of which (113 photographs) are contained in the sub-category Music and Musicians. Of particular note are numerous photos of community brass bands, a photo of John Philip Sousa and his band at Grand Circus Park (no. 122); an image of the inventor Charles Crawford and his patented "Pickaphone" mechanism for playing stringed instruments, ca. 1888 (no. 123); and copy prints of two important early jazz bands, Finney’s Orchestra (no. 131) and McKinney’s Cotton Pickers (no. 132).
Portraits:
505 photographs. Material is divided into the following sub-categories: Individuals (172 photographs), Groups (133 photographs), Children (97 photographs), Weddings (64 photographs), Confirmation and Communion (41 photographs). Of particular interest are a photograph of Joan Baxter and her Hot Dog Cooker (no. 137); three 1860's portraits of members of the Hawley family of Detroit (no. 141), one of which is inscribed with enlargement instructions ca.1901 on its verso; and a portrait of politician and founder of the Republican Party Zachariah Chandler, taken by Benjamin Powelson ca. 1880 (no. 142).
Of the many notable images within the Groups category are an outstanding image of sixteen Packard Motor Car Company employees piled onto a 1911 Packard in front of the then new Packard factory on West Grand Blvd. (no. 144.9); a group of African American women engaged in a ceremonial burning of the mortgage of the Phyllis Wheatley Home for Aged Colored Ladies (no. 162); and a portrait of members of the Direct Credits Society, a Great Depression-era wealth redistribution movement founded by Alfred Lawson (no. 166).
Parades:
54 photographs. Many scenes of massive parades in Detroit. Of note is a series of photographs of women marching in a racially-integrated United Spanish War Veterans Parade, ca.1940 (no. 179); and a view of five young women in a florally decorated early automobile (no. 180.11).
Business & Commerce:
319 photographs. Where possible, material has been divided into the following sub-categories: Business Exteriors (52 photographs), Business Interiors (125 photographs), Construction (22 photographs), Ford Motor Company (19 photographs). Of note is an image of a group of brewers tapping a keg at the Marx Brewing Co. (no. 186.1); Candler Dock & Dredge Co. workers and surveyors building a dock, taken by the Manning Bros. ca 1920s (no. 192); women rolling cigars at the R.G. Dunn factory, 1909 (no. 204); workers fabricating automobile bodies at the Briggs Manufacturing Co. ca. 1910s (no. 206);interior view of the Burroughs Adding Machine factory (no 209.11); the Penobscot Building construction in three stages ca 1928 (no. 217); and two fold-out panoramic photos of the Ford complex at River Rouge taken by Otto Rotch in 1925 (no. 218).
Views:
86 photographs. Material is divided into Street Views (28 photographs), Residential Views (51 photographs), and Aerial Views (7 photographs).
Architecture:
69 photographs. Of particular note is a charming view of a small inn at Springwells, Mich., the International Exposition House ca. 1889 (no. 235); an 1870's print of the large Russell House Hotel in Detroit (no. 238); and a panoramic view of downtown Detroit at its peak, taken by the Murray Studio in the 1920s (no. 240.18).
Labor & Unemployment:
8 photographs primarily focused on unemployment during the Great Depression. Of note is a group photo of the striking Journeyman Bakers International Union in 1902 (no. 248).
Athletes & Athletics:
58 photographs. Of particular note are a copy-print of a 1910 Detroit Tigers team photo featuring Hall of Famer Ty Cobb (no. 261); a series of 3 group photographs of an early soccer team, Michigan Alkali F.C. in 1923 (no. 265); Wyandotte baseball teams (no. 266);. The Slocum’s Island baseball champions of 1882 (no. 272.4); and a 1943 curling team (no. 273).
Classrooms & Schools:
38 photographs. Of particular interest are a student group in front of a one-room schoolhouse at Cherry Hill in 1934 (no. 280.11); a kindergarten band at Clippert School taken by the Manning Bros. (no. 280.20); and a ca.1936 Lincoln Park High School album with personal snapshots and autographs of classmates (no. 279).
Places of Worship & Religious Activities:
43 photographs. One of several images related to African American church congregations shows members of an A.M.E. church dressed in "traditional" African garb ca.1920-1930 (no. 284).
Parks:
112 photographs. Of particular focus is Belle Isle (approx. 50 photographs) and Waterworks Park. A series of Belle Isle views taken in 1889 by Holcombe & Metzen is particularly picturesque (no. 297.1-9).
Funerals & Postmortem Photography:
14 photographs. These photographs date from the 1910s-1930s and are mostly photographs of open caskets surrounded by the deceased's family.
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 1 (Box 1)
  - 1. [X-ray of teeth, ca. 1930], 1 photograph
  - 2. [16 real photo stamps], 16 real photo stamps
  - 3. [Bartell residence and family photos, ca. 1950s], 9 photographs
  - 4. The Stratosphere Gondola [movie prop, ca. 1934, NOTE: see image #31 for related content], 1 photograph
  - 5. Wyandotte 75 years of good clean living [booklet], 1 booklet
  - 6. Souvenir of Detroit, the convention city ca. 1905, 1 booklet, photomechanical prints
  - 7. Detroit in 1898, 1 photograph
  - 8. [Firefighters fighting a fire at the Sparling Plastic Industries building, ca. 1961], 1 photograph
  - 9. [Children's party, ca. 1890s], 1 photograph
  - 10. Reversible Ventura Fan and adjustable frame [woman cooking in kitchen ca. 1920s], 1 photograph
  - 11. [Detroit snapshot photo albums, ca. 1950s], 36 photographs in 4 booklets
  - 12. [Miscellaneous Detroit snapshots, ca. 1950s], 35 photographs
  - 13. [Knights of Pythias encampment, Detroit, August 1900], 3 photographs [2 additional photos of Indiana encampment]
  - 14. [John F. Kennedy-Robert F. Kennedy composite photo in Detroit by Tony Spina, ca. 1960s], 1 photograph
  - 15. [Dr. Rydzewski collection, appears to be family photographs ca. 1905-1961 also 1921 letter from Lithuania written in Polish], 37 photographs, 4 ephemera
  - 16. Detroit Illustrated [published by H. R. Page & Co., 1889], 101 pages, photomechanical prints
  - 17. Detroit Journal explosion [November 1895], 1 photograph
  - 18. [Michigan infantry unit in park, ca. 1890s], 1 photograph
  - 19. [Woman demonstrating range and stove ca. 1900-1910], 2 photographs
  - 20. [Miscellaneous nightclub souvenir photos], 28 photographs
  - 21. [Panorama of Grand Circus Park, ca. 1925], 1 photograph
  - 22. [1967 Detroit Riot, copy prints of Associated Press photographs], 3 photographs
  - 23. [Soap Box Derby competition], 11 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 2 (Box 2)
  - 24. [Two women standing next to rock sculpture; view of boarding house(?), ca. 1890-1910], 2 photographs
  - 25. [Women eating outside on picnic table, ca. 1920s-1930s], 1 photograph
  - 26. [Livestock at the Detroit stockyards, ca. 1920s], 2 photographs
  - 27. [Photographs taken by Edison Institute student, possibly Louis Ives, showing basketball game, school dance, and group portrait ca. 1946-47], 4 photographs
  - 28. [Full-sized replica of Naval ship on display in Grand Circus Park, ca. 1942 (see image 36.16 for different angle of same replica ship)], 1 photograph
  - 29. [Snapshots of Detroit freeway construction, ca. 1957], 52 photographs
  - 30. [Miscellaneous Detroit architecture (incl. Temple Beth El, Detroit City Hall, Waterworks Park), shipping on the Detroit river, street scenes, and transportation, ca. 1900-1910], 16 photographs
  - 31. [Henry Ford with stratosphere scientists Jean Picard and Jeanette Picard, ca. 1934, NOTE: see image #4 for related content], 1 photograph
  - 32. [President of Suburban Goodfellows selling papers to make food baskets for the poor, 1927], 1 photograph
  - 33. [Detroit policeman directing traffic on Woodward Ave, ca. 1918], 1 photograph
  - 34. [Collection of photographs by Brown City photographer Clarence L. Hoffman, miscellaneous subjects including a street view of Jefferson Ave in Detroit, ca. 1900-10], 12 photographs
  - 35. [Collection of photographs by unidentified photographer, ca. 1905, only one is from Detroit, a photograph of the Majestic Building, the rest are identified as being from Brown City, Mich.], 7 photographs
  - 36. [Detroit snapshots ca. 1942 including photograph (36.16) from different angle of same replica ship as in item #28, also one picture (36.1) of Burton Memorial Tower in Ann Arbor, Mich.], 16 photographs
  - 37. [Miscellaneous Detroit street views, groups of people and architecture, appear to have once been pasted in a scrapbook, ca. 1910s], 13 photographs
  - 38. ["Standard" Jacks and garage equipment, ca. 1929], 4 photographs, 1 ephemera
  - 39. [Researchers in the Reference Room at the old Detroit Public Library, ca. 1910], 1 photograph
  - 40. [Two male laboratory workers working on experiment, ca. 1950s], 1 photograph
  - 41. [Fred A. Anstie Collection, mostly of Anstie and railroad coworkers, trains, and a retirement party for Anstie ca. 1970], 35 photographs, 5 ephemera
  - 42. [Interior of Greenfield Village tintype studio ca. 1980(?)], 1 photograph
  - 43. [1898 group portrait of Company C, 35th Regiment Michigan Volunteers, woman seated with regiment], 1 photograph
  - 44. [Aftermath of fire at unidentified automobile factory, ca. 1900-10], 6 photographs
  - 45. [Aftermath of fire at Saxon Motor Car Company, February 1917], 10 photographs
  - 46. [Detroit News photographers and photographic equipment], 25 photographs
  - 47. [Misc. Detroit views ca. 1920], 8 photographs
  - 48. [Two portraits of Dr. Jonathan R. Bowers, ca. 1870s], 2 photographs, 5 ephemera
  - 49. [WWJ Radio equipment and staff], 6 photographs
  - 50. [Copy prints, panorama of Detroit riverfront ca. 1880], 5 photographs
  - 51. [Detroit News photographic equipment, demonstrated by John Orris, ca. 1957], 3 photographs
  - 52. [View of Detroit River with Ambassador Bridge in the distance], 1 photograph
  - 53. [Razing of Uniroyal Tire plant, ca. 1985], 1 photograph
  - 54. [Detroit News executive office, ca. 1922], 1 photograph
  - 55. [Firefighters battle fire at the corner of Campus Martius and Monroe, 1897], 1 photograph
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 3 (Box 3)
  - Transportation -- Automobiles & Trucks
  - 56. [1952 city of Dearborn taxi driver license], 1 photograph
  - 57. [Armored truck or tank, Army recruitment ca. 1918], 1 photograph
  - 58. [City Treasurer pay car], 1 photograph
  - 59. [Geml-McGrath Dairy Inc. trucks], 1 photograph
  - 60. [Auto rally, ca. 1911], 3 photographs
  - 61. [Gardner-White Co. delivery truck, ca. 1930], 1 photograph
  - 62. [Advertisement "Important Cadillac Firsts"], 1 photograph
  - 63. [Carter Automobile, ca. 1910], 3 photographs, 1 newspaper article
  - 64. [Sauer Cooperage delivery truck], 1 photograph
  - 65. [Booth Insulation Co. delivery trucks], 3 photographs
  - 66. [Miscellaneous automobile businesses], 6 photographs
  - 67. [Wayne Creamery delivery truck, July 12, 1928], 1 photograph
  - 68. [Delivery trucks for Marcel Blomme Butter, Eggs & Cheese], 1 photograph
  - 69. [Trucks and automobiles], 25 photographs
  - 70. [Enlargement of automobile stereographs], 2 photographs
  - 71. [Individuals and families posed with cars, incl. African-American couple], 5 photographs
  - Transportation -- Aircraft
  - 72. [Mary Elizabeth Von Mach, first Detroit women to own and operate her own airplane, ca. 1920s], 2 photographs
  - 73. [Aircraft], 10 photographs
  - 74. [Miscellaneous images of hot air balloons at Detroit News race, ca. 1926-27], 3 photographs
  - 75. [Planes on display at the National Aircraft Show at Detroit City Airport ca. 1931], 1 photograph
  - 76. [Panorama of Stout Airplane Co. and Henry Ford Airport], 1 photograph
  - 77. Helicopter delivering film to the Detroit News, 1 photograph
  - Transportation -- Railroads &Trains
  - 78. [Railroad at Wyandotte, ca. 1920s], 8 photographs
  - 79. Electrification of Ford's Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad, 1 photograph
  - 80. [Michigan Central Terminal, Detroit under construction], 2 identical digital copy prints
  - 81. [Locomotives, railroads and depots], 23 photographs
  - 82. [Miscellaneous locomotives, railroads, depots, and offices, ca. 1920s-1970s], 24 photographs
  - Transportation -- Streetcars & Trolleys
  - 83. [Miscellaneous street railroads, ca. 1890s-1930s], 16 photographs
  - 84. [Grosse Pointe-Waterworks Park streetcar line, ca. 1891], 4 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 4 (Box 4)
  - Transportation -- Roads & Infrastructure
  - 85. [Towers used in construction of Livingstone Canal, ca. 1912], 1 photograph
  - 86. [Copy photograph of 19th century toll road, Jefferson at Baldwin], 1 photograph
  - 87. [Cars and bike on Tireman Ave east of what is now Greenfield Rd, ca. 1920s], 1 photograph
  - 88. [Bridge over Connor Creek on Gratiot Ave, ca. 1913], 1 photograph
  - 89. [Aerial view of Fort Street Highway, ca. 1930], 1 photograph
  - 90. [Traffic signal proposal at Gratiot and Van Dyke ca. 1930s-1940s], 2 photographs
  - 91. Michigan Ave at Scotten before widening [ca. 1940], 2 photographs
  - 92. [Woodward Avenue between Six and Seven Mile Road, before and after paving, ca. 1909], 2 photographs
  - 93. [West Jefferson Avenue-Rouge River Bridge], 2 photographs
  - 94. [Bridge at Grand Lawn Cemetery, ca. 1921], 1 photograph
  - 95. [Detroit-Windsor Michigan Central Railroad tunnel construction], 19 photographs, 1 ephemera
  - Transportation -- Wagons
  - 96. [Alfred Easter City Creamery delivery wagons and workers, ca. 1893], 2 photographs
  - 97. [F.M. Sibley Lumber Co. wagon and worker], 1 photograph
  - 98. [Goebel's Brewing Co. horse-drawn delivery wagons ca. 1900-1910], 3 photographs
  - 99. [Miscellaneous horse-drawn delivery wagons], 14 photographs
  - Transportation -- Maritime
  - 100. [10th district light house depot, ca. 1890s], 1 photograph
  - 101. [Crowd onboard railroad ferry, ca. 1930s], 1 photograph, 1 negative
  - 102 [Ship launching-Yosemite, ca. 1901], 2 photographs
  - 103. [Woman onboard railroad ferry, ca. 1902], 1 photograph
  - 104. [Worker group on unidentified dredge], 1 photograph
  - 105. [Aerial view of the Detroit Yacht Club], 1 photograph
  - 106. [Men onboard City of Cleveland III, ca. 1910s], 1 photograph
  - 107. [Worker group on dredge, Hercules, Dunbar Sullivan Dredging Co.], 1 photograph
  - 108. [Photograph of painting of City of Detroit steamboat, ca. 1880s], 1 photograph
  - 109. [Ship launching-Merton E. Farr, ca. 1920], 2 photographs
  - 110. [Steamboat Tashmoo in Detroit River, ca. 1900], 1 photograph
  - 111. [Speed boat races, ca. 1945-1955], 6 photographs
  - 112. [Steamboats-Greyhound and Eastern States, ca. 1910s], 3 photographs
  - 113. [Steamboat-Western States, photographs are taken over a range of dates], 3 photographs
  - 114. [Miscellaneous boats], 13 photographs
  - Performers
  - 115. [Circus performers, ca. 1930s], 4 photographs
  - 116. Pike Theatre Co. [composite group portrait, ca. 1902], 1 photograph
  - 117. [Sonny Elliot and chimpanzee, ca. 1960s], 1 photograph
  - 118. Earl Yoke [entertainer, ca. 1910s], 2 photographs
  - 119. [Miscellaneous individual performers], 8 photographs
  - 120. [Miscellaneous costumed groups and portraits], 13 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 5 (Box 5)
  - Performers -- Music & Musicians
  - 121. Non-Partisan Progressive Band [ca. 1930s-1940s], 4 photographs
  - 122. [John Philip Sousa at Grand Circus Park, ca. 1928], 1 photograph
  - 123. [Charles Crawford and his "pickaphone", mechanism for playing stringed instruments, ca. 1888], 1 photograph, 1 ephemera
  - 124. [Miscellaneous individual musicians], 7 photographs
  - 125. Leonard B. Smith with Philco Band, December 13, 1944, 5 photographs and ephemera
  - 126. [Detroit Symphony woodwind ensemble], 16 photographs, 5 booklets and clippings
  - 127. [Miscellaneous band groups], 37 photographs, 1 ephemera
  - 128. African-American junior choir and orchestra, Second Baptist Church, September 14, 1923, 1 photograph
  - 129. [Portrait of Benjamin Shook, African-American jazz band leader, ca. 1920], 2 photographs
  - 130. Ypsilanti Normal Choir, Frederick Alexander Conductor, at Detroit Symphony Christmas Concert, December 15, 1929, 1 photograph
  - 131. [Copy print of African-American jazz band Finney's Orchestra, Fred S. Stone Manager], 2 photographs
  - 132. [Copy prints of African-American jazz band McKinney's Cotton Pickers, ca. 1926], 14 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 6 (Box 6)
  - Portraits -- Individuals
  - 133.1-133.68 [Misc. portraits-women], 68 of 80 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 7 (Box 7)
  - Portraits -- Individuals (cont.)
  - 133.69-133.80 [Misc. portraits-women], 12 of 80 photographs
  - 134.1-134.52 [Misc. portraits-men], 52 of 78 photographs
- David V. Tinder collection of Michigan photography, County File, Wayne County, Box 8 (Box 8)
  - Portraits -- Individuals (cont.)